A Guide to the Lyman Creighton Craig papers, Rockefeller University Faculty FA134
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Subject Files, 3
  - NMR Consortium correspondence, 1968-1974 (Box 18)
    Dr. Gibbons presents paper and in 1972 Apr 19-20 Pasadena, Calif, Caltech, NIH sponsored workshop on magnetic resonance in biological systems. Gibbons "The application of magnetic resonance technique to determine the structure of a cyclic peptide". Includes program.
    1971 November 9: Peter Ziegler and Hartwig Aim memo (copy) "Location of NMR machines of the spectroscopy dept, Dr. Gibbons"
    1973 November 5: Drs. Field, Agosta, Craig, King and Merrifield to Dr. Seitz (copy) giving a statement "of positions as chemists on matters of staffing and future activities of the RU NMR facility"
    - 1968-1970 (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - 1971-1974 (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - NMR consortium - NSF grant, 1969-1974; 2 folders (Box 18)
    Awarded for consortium support. Includes correspondence, grant proposals, award notices, progress reports, acctg records and final reports.
    - 1969-1970 (Box 18, Folder 3)
    - 1971-1974 (Box 18, Folder 4)
      Includes 1971 June 18 Congressman Edward I. Koch to L.C. Craig letter of congratulation on NSF grant award.
  - NMR consortium - Billing, 1971 March-1974 November (Box 18, Folder 5)
    Billing for professional services rendered by NMR consortium.
  - NMR consortium - Acctg. records, 1969 November- 1974 April (lacks 1972 July-1972 September) (Box 18, Folder 6)
    Acctg. dept monthly print out sheets summaries of charges and payments for services rendered by consortium.
  - NMR consortium - Catalogs (Box 18, Folder 7)
    Catalogs of various equipment.
    Arranged in alphabetical order of company.
  - Office of Scientific Research and Development (O.S.R.D.) (Box 19)
    Dr. Craig member of National Defense Committee of the Office of Scientific Research and Development (O.S.R.D.).
    This committee established to ensure the purity of atabrine and other chemical products' for the armed forces. W.M. Clarke, Chairman of Division of chemistry and chemical technology (NRC). Other committee members include: E. Cowles Andrus, Paul D. Bartlett, Raymond N. Bieter, Herbert O. Calvery, E.M.K. Geilung, Walter A. Jacobs, E.Q. King, E.K. Marshall Jr., Lyndon F. Small, Frank H. Wiley, and Robert B. Woodward.
    - Correspondence, 1940-1946
      Includes correspondence with Lewis H. Weed (filed with Clarke, W.M.) Chairman, Division of medical science (NRC) and a note "Work done during W.W. II period 1942-1945 for O.S.R.D. and others L.C. Craig" (handwritten) but not obviously O.S.R.D. contract. In 3 folders.
      Arranged by Dr. Craig in alphabetical order.
      - Appointment (Box 19, Folder 1)
      - Correspondence A - J (Box 19, Folder 2)
      - Correspondence K - Z (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Sloan-Kettering Institute for Cancer Research (S-K), 1970-1974 (Box 19)
    1970 August: Dr. Craig becomes member of Board of scientific consultants of S-K.
    Correspondence and duplicated material as working member of board and also indicates collaboration between S-K and RU.
    Includes: Membership lists; Agendas of meetings with biographical data of S-K staff members presenting annual reports of investigative work and recent publications with Craig handwritten notes in some instances.
    - Special interest items
      - Frank L. Horsfall report to S-K board of trustees (copy): Summary of progress, change in program 1971, 1970 December 18
      - Recommendations for G. Palade and I. Tamm for Presidency and Directorship of S-K
      - Arrangements by Craig for G.B. Brown of S-K address to RU organic discussion group on the "Carcinogenic purines: their chemistry", 1971 February
      - announcement on Robert A. Good Presidency of S-K, 1972 March 30
      - L.C. Craig handwritten evaluation of J.D. Fissekis, 1973 June 19
        Includes curriculum vitae, bibliography, 4 reprints by Fissekis et al and 1 duplicated ms In 3 folders:.
    - Correspondence
      - 1970-1971 March (Box 19, Folder 4)
      - 1971 June-1972 (Box 19, Folder 5)
      - 1973 June-1974 June (Box 19, Folder 6)
- RU administration, 4
  - Academic Council and Senate, 1967-1969; 2 folders (Box 20)
    Dr. Craig as member of Academic Council and Senate involved in many committees to shape policy of RU.
    Served on committees to:
    Review policies and practices regarding faculty appointments and promotions (Kenneth M. Case, Philip D'Alesandro, Leo V. DiCara, Wm. K. Estes, Albert Gold, Margeris A. Jesaitis, Richard M. Krause, Alexander Mauro, David Mauzerall, Robert L. Schoenfeld, David Ypbantis, John B. Zabriskie).
    Deal with bio-medical sciences.
    Chemical Sciences Committee (Chairman). (This appears to be outgrowth of Committee to consider the graduate program in organic chemistry and biochemistry [See box 20]).
    File made up of miscellaneous correspondence and duplicated material of: announcements, agendas, minutes of meetings. Also includes reports of various committees (copies).
    Craig served on Committess to review policies and practices regarding faculty appointments and promotions.
    - 1967-1968 May (Box 20, Folder 1)
    - 1968 June-1969 (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - Faculty committee to consider the program in organic chemistry and biochemistry, 1965-1972; 2 folders (Box 20)
    In 1969 Dr. Craig becomes chairman (Wm. Stein original chairman). In 1965 Dr. Craig also chairman of subcommittee to consider curriculum in organic chemistry. Includes duplicated material of: proposal to aid organizing committee; minutes of meetings; outline of student courses. Dr. Craig gives course in organic qualitative analysis and lecture on "countercurrent distribution" as part of biochemistry curriculum; student examinations in organic chemistry and some exam results; reading lists. As committee member Dr. Craig involved in making lecture and other arrangements; some for faculty appointments. Includes background material for possible appointment of: Daniel Steinberg, Jerome Vinograd, Peter Von Hippel, and suggestions for other possible appointments. [See also under: Academic council and senate in box no. 20 for Chemical Sciences Committee].
    - 1965-1966 May (Box 20, Folder 3)
    - 1966 June-1972 (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - Isotope Committee, 1963-1968 1971 (Box 20, Folder 5)
    Deals primarily with seeking permission for members of Craig lab to work with radioactive isotopes and 1971 July items on NSF site visit involving needed equipment for isotope lab.
  - Spectroscopy committee and laboratory, 1958-1968 (Box 20, Folder 6)
    In 1965 Dr. Craig becomes chairman of Spectroscopy committee. Deals primarily with operating spectroscopy laboratory. Includes minutes of meetings chaired by Dr. Craig; purchase of equipment; deferment of needed personnel.
    Special interest items include:.
    - Handwritten undated "History of spectrofluoremeter proposals"
    - Spectroscopic laboratory budget proposals submitted by Herbert Jaffe, 1959 July 1-1960 June 30
      Includes budget proposals, budgets, correspondence with lab heads about use and purchase of equipment; hiring personnel; instrument pamphlets [Pages removed from original black notebook].
    - Stanford Moore to L.C. Craig. Views on administering a spectroscopy lab, 1965 June 14
  - RU students, 1957-1974 (Box 21, Folder 1)
    Primarily with Dean of Students Frank Brink. Dr. Craig member of Dean's committee for academic affairs. Includes progress reports, course work, thesis examinations and evaluations, reports on prospective student interviews. Also includes reports on student performance in "Qualitative organic analysis" course given by Dr. Craig with some student reports; photocopies of applications for admission to RU graduate program and 1972 Peterson Guide for Graduate Study RU entry sheets with chart. The following list of graduate students have individual files under correspondence:.
    Bennett and Bockman included in alphabetical listing but no individual files.
    Bennett, T.P.
    Bockman, R.
    Cerami, A.
    Eaker, D.
    Englund, P.T.
    Galardy, R.
    Guidotti, G.
    Laiken, S.
    Meinardi, H.
    Rasmussen, H.
    Rifkin, D.B.
    Ruttenberg, M.
    Schleich, T.W.
    Simon, S.
    Smith, A.B.
    Sogn, J.A.
    Spencer, M.
    Stern, A.
    Williams, R.
  - RU students lectures; courses (some for faculty), 1955-1967 (Box 21, Folder 2)
    Primarily deals with lectures by RU faculty and others as part of student courses; some lectures for faculty. Dr. Craig appears to be on committee planning biochemistry course and its lectures. Includes some items on lecture arrangements with outside guest lecturers. Indications are Dr. Craig involved in arrangements for guest lecturers.
    - Student lectures given by Dr. Craig
      - "The chemical approach to the study of natural products", 1955 October 24-25
      - "Chemistry of natural products", 1957 November 14-15
        Includes reading list.
      - "The structure of natural products", 1958 October 6-10
        Includes lecture outlines.
      - "The structure of natural products", 1959 October 19-23
        Includes lectures outline, working material, handwritten notes, what appears to be handwritten lecture outlines by others, one marked "Merrifield".
  - Bronk, Detlev W., 1954-1972 (Box 21, Folder 3)
    Correspondence includes ca. 1956 Oct 5 for July 1955-June 1956 annual report handwritten list by Dr. Craig on meetings attended and lectures delivered during this period; working plans for physical organic chemistry course; recommendations for Dr. Locke salary increase and Dr. Rothen promotion; on Dr. Craig serving on various RI committees.
  - Campbell, Charles I., 1957-1962 (Box 21, Folder 4)
    Primarily listings of activities for publication in RI Quarterly.
  - Elliot, R.C., 1943 1958-1968 (Box 21, Folder 5)
    Deals with miscellaneous matters including lab equipment; hospital insurance; course budgets; 1969 listing of faculty members connected with Craig laboratory.
  - Flinn, Waldo R., 1954-1957 1962-1965 (Box 21, Folder 6)
    Includes item about Wolfgang Papperitz employment as glassblower; 1962 Christmas Lectures and budget request for Dr. Craig's "Organic qualitative analysis" course.
  - Gasser, H.S., 1953 (Box 21, Folder 7)
    Copy of Dr. Craig's statement on "Present scope of the scientific work" for Pamphlet.
  - Gold, Albert, 1970-1974 (Box 21, Folder 8)
    Primarily about laboratory space and equipment.
  - McCarty, Maclyn, 1966-1969 (Box 21, Folder 9)
    Correspondence deals with Committee of biomedical sciences research support grant to consider the manner in which grant to be used. Dr. Craig member of committee. Includes copy of minutes of first meeting. Also includes correspondence about purchase and construction of equipment and travel allowance.
  - Registrar (Marion E. Lucius, Registrar), 1964-1974 (Box 21, Folder 10)
    Includes: notices of Craig laboratory faculty appointments, promotions, departures and adjunct appointments of members of NMR consortium and faculty members working in NMR laboratory; 1969-70, 1970-71, 1971-72, 1972-73 RU catalog entries for Craig laboratory.
  - Rivers, Thomas M., 1954-1955 (Box 21, Folder 11)
    Deals primarily with new CCD apparatus.
  - Seitz, Frederick, 1969-1974 (Box 22, Folder 1)
    Deals with university matters of appointments, promotions, budgets, retirement policies (Dr. Craig member of committee on retirement policies). Includes duplicated material, some on University senate and academic council. Also includes copies of some correspondence with Dr. Seitz from other faculty members.
    Special interest items:.
    - Dr. Craig's replies up to 1969 to Dr. Seitz requests for information of last 15 years of outstanding alumni and most significant scientific and scholarly accomplishment of Craig lab and RU at large, 1969 September 16
    - Duplicated copies of correspondence from S. Moore to F. Seitz on campus situation, 1970 May
    - Recommendations of F. Westheimer and H. Rasmussen to RU Board of Trustees
    - As member of RU student programs agrees to visit and lecture at a few colleges to stimulate interest in student program, 1972 October
      Includes copy of abstract of "The isolation and structure determination of active principles" with short biographical sketch of Craig.
  - Smith, Edric B. (Business manager), 1954-1955 (Box 22, Folder 2)
    Includes budgeting for CCD apparatus.
  - Whitaker, Douglas, 1957-1964 (Box 22, Folder 3)
    Miscellaneous administrative correspondence includes: laboratory personnel, faculty appointments, purchasing equipment, allocating funds (budgets), travel expenses, use of radio isotopes.
  - Laboratory (Box 22)
    Under this subject includes alphabetical listing of:.
    - Budgets, 1952-1974 (Box 22, Folder 4)
      Budgets 1952-1953; 1954-1955; 1965-1966 and acctg department print out sheets of budgets for 1971-72; 1972-1973; 1973-74 and 1974 July transaction report.
    - Chemicals (Box 22, Folder 5)
      Includes organic and inorganic chemicals master list (chemical, room no., location).
    - Equipment, 1960-1974 (Box 22, Folder 6)
      Primarily purchase orders for service contracts and repair of laboratory equipment.
    - Efforts reports, 1972-1974 (Box 22, Folder 7)
      Reports of professional staff time allotted to grant and university funds.
    - Personnel (Box 22, Folder 8)
      Includes some vacation schedules and recommendations for non-faculty personnel.
    - Plans (By Buildings and Grounds), 1958-1966 (Box 22, Folder 9)
      Includes copies of schematic drawings of plans and alterations for various Craig laboratories.
    - Procedures: chemicals-disposable (hazardous, explosive etc), 1971 June 10 (Box 22, Folder 10)
      In 1961 Dr. Craig with W.H. Stein and S. Moore prepares memo "Hazardous chemicals and 1963 memo "On the alleged hazards of Teflon". Includes copies of memos and 1971 June 10 inventory "Listing of hazardous chemicals".
    - Purchase orders, 1968-1974 (Box 22, Folder 11)
      Records of Craig laboratory purchases ordered and received in 1 bound black notebook.
    - Shop orders, 1969-1974 (Box 22, Folder 12)
      For yearly general maintenance by the various shops and other work done in laboratory.
    - Shops and services: Instrument shop (Box 22, Folder 13)
      In 1960 Dr. Craig becomes chairman of standing committee of the faculty on the instrument shops.
      In 1963 name changed to Standing faculty shop committee.
      Includes 1961, 1962 and 1963 minutes of meetings.
    - Shops and Services Publications. Correspondence with Florence Stewart about Craig and members of Craig laboratory publications for the Studies (Box 22, Folder 14)
    - Travel vouchers, [undated] 1953 1955 1958-1973 (Box 22, Folder 15)
      Primarily travel vouchers for meetings attended by Dr. Craig and members of laboratory.
  - Correspondence, 1 box (Box 22a)
    This box of correspondence was added to the Craig papers from the Faculty Records office.
    Shows complete employment history application for employment, some photographs and correspondence with administrative officers from 1933 and continues with Mrs. Craig after Dr. Craig's death.
    - Employment application and record; photographs (Box 22a, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 1933-1959 (Box 22a, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, 1960-1975 (Box 22a, Folder 3)
  - Student dissertations. Work done in Craig laboratory. In some instances other members of laboratory research advisor, 2 boxes
    Arranged in alphabetical order by student name.
    - Eaker, D.L. (Box 23, Folder 1)
    - Englund, P.T. (Box 23, Folder 2)
    - Galardy, R. (Box 23, Folder 3)
    - Laiken, S. (Box 23, Folder 4)
    - Rifkin, D.B. (Box 23, Folder 5)
    - Simon, S.R. (Box 23, Folder 6)
    - Schleich, T.W. (Box 24, Folder 1)
    - Spencer, E.M. (Box 24, Folder 2)
    - Stern, A. (Box 24, Folder 3)
  - NIH Grants, 1958-1974; 3 folders (Box 25)
    Correspondence includes grant applications, award notices, final expenditure reports, research progress reports by investigators in Craig laboratory for some years for grant renewal applications. Also includes correspondence about purchasing equipment, travel allowances, appointments, salaries, inventions by Craig and others and duplicated material.
    - 1958-1963 (Box 25, Folder 1)
    - 1964-1967 (Box 25, Folder 2)
    - 1967 July-1974 (Box 25, Folder 3)
  - NIH Grants - Accounting records, 2 folders (Box 25)
    Related Materials
    See also under: NIH-NIAMD for grant applications in box no. 17.
    Includes some purchase orders.
    - 1958 September-1962 (Box 25, Folder 4)
    - 1963-1970 (Box 25, Folder 5)
  - NIH - Training Grants, 1962 1969 (Box 25, Folder 6)
    Correspondence includes 1962 grant application to provide postdoctoral training in biochemistry. Submitted but not approved. Also includes expenditure reports to NIH on 1967-68 A. Rimon training grant.
  - NSF Grants, 1962-1964 (Box 25, Folder 7)
    Correspondence includes grant application, award notice, acctg fiscal reports.
  - NSF Grants - Accounting records (some purchase orders) 1962-1963; 1969-1970 (no record of NSF grant for these years) (Box 25, Folder 8)
    [See also under: Marfey, P.S. in box no. 8].
- Manuscript materials, 1948-1976; 5
  Include annual scientific reports; laboratory notes; working papers; publications not listed in Craig bibliography and conference information cited for publications presented at conferences or meetings. Also includes some mss with no publication information [NPI] and an unidentified ms.
  Arranged in chronological order by publication date.
  - Annual scientific reports (Box 26)
    - (W.A. Jacobs), 1948-1949 (Box 26, Folder 1)
    - 1950 (Box 26, Folder 1)
    - 1951 (Box 26, Folder 1)
    - 1952 (Box 26, Folder 1)
    - 1953 (Box 26, Folder 1)
    - 1954 (Box 26, Folder 1)
      Includes annual and lay scientific report (with photograph of countercurrent distribution apparatus).
    - 1955 (Box 26, Folder 1)
      Includes annual and lay scientific reports.
    - 1955-1956 (Box 26, Folder 1)
    - 1957-1967 (Box 26, Folder 1)
      Lacking.
    - 1968-1969 (Box 26, Folder 2)
    - Organic chemistry annual report, 1969-1970 (Box 26, Folder 2)
      Includes Agosta et al handwritten report and 2 unidentified handwritten reports.
    - Organic chemistry annual report, 1970-1971 (Box 26, Folder 2)
      Includes reports by spectroscopy laboratory by Agosta et al; M. Printz; T.P. King and T.P. Hettinger reports.
    - 1971-1972 (Box 26, Folder 2)
    - 1972-1973 (Box 26, Folder 2)
      Includes reports by spectroscopy lab; T.P. King; H.E. Bleich; J. Sogn, the Bruker HX90 (NMR) machine and use.
    - Listing of papers published by Craig and others in laboratory, 1967-1974 (Box 26, Folder 2)
  - L.C. Craig and D. Craig "Extraction and distribution", 1950 (Box 26, Folder 3)
    In: Weissberger, A., ed., Technique of organic chemistry. New York, Interscience Publishers, v. 3, pp. 171-311. Copy with corrections (pp. 244-311). Questionably 1950? (See 1956 edition) [Reprint of this chapter not with collected papers].
  - L.C. Craig, W. Hausmann, E.H. Ahrens and E.J. Harfenist "Determination of weight curves in column processes", 1951 (Box 26, Folder 4)
    Analytical chemistry 23, 1326-1327 Figure 1 only.
  - L.C. Craig, W. Hausmann and J.R. Weisiger. "The molecular weight of bacitracin A", 1953 (Box 26, Folder 5)
    J biol chem 200, 765-773.
    Correspondence and abstract of paper.
  - L.C. Craig "The use of small-scale fractionation techniques for characterization of complex organic compounds", 1954 (Box 26, Folder 6)
    Record of chemical progress 14, 177-189. Presented at 1953 Nov 9 Detroit, Mich. Friends of the Kresge-Hooker Scientific Library/Wayne "Frontiers in chemistry" lecture series.
  - L.C. Craig, W. Hausmann and J.R. Weisiger "Structural studies with bacitracin A", 1954 (Box 26, Folder 7)
    JACS 76, 2839-2840.
    Correspondence and copy of ms.
  - L.C. Craig (Book review) Hecker, Erich, Ed., Verteilungsverhahren im laboratorium zu "Angewandte chemie" und "Chemie-ingenieur-technik", 1955 (Box 26, Folder 8)
    Arch biochem biophys 59, 541.
    Correspondence and copy of review.
  - D. Theodoropoulos and L.C. Craig "The synthesis of several isoleucyl peptides and certain of their properties", 1955 (Box 26, Folder 9)
    J org chem 20, 1169-1172.
    Correspondence; copy of ms with corrections; working material.
  - T.P. King and L.C. Craig "The chemistry of tyrocidine. IV. Purification and characterization of tyrocidine B", 1955 (Box 26, Folder 10)
    JACS 77, 6624-6627.
    Copy of ms; photographs of figures and reprint of published paper.
  - T.P. King and L.C. Craig "The chemistry of tyrocidine. V. The amino acid sequence of tyrocidine B", 1955 (Box 26, Folder 11)
    JACS 77, 6627-6630.
    Copy of ms and photograph of figure.
  - L.C. Craig "Antibiotic polypeptides", 1956 (Box 26, Folder 12)
    In: Int'l Cong Biochem, 3rd, Brussels, 1955. New York, Academic Press, pp. 416-421.
    Correspondence; copy of presentation with corrections; reprint of published ms; (on last page of reprint - (front and back): contents, sectional reports, list of contributors).
  - L.C. Craig, T.P. King and A. Stracher "Dialysis studies. II. Some experiments dealing with the problem of selectivity", 1957 (Box 26, Folder 13)
    JACS 79, 3729-3737.
    1 item, correspondence and copy of ms.
  - W. Hausmann and L.C. Craig "Countercurrent distribution of serum albumin", 1958 (Box 26, Folder 14)
    JACS 80, 2703-2710.
    1 item correspondence; referee 1 comments on ms and graphs dated 1957 Apr-Oct.
  - L.C. Craig, W. Konigsberg, A. Stracher and T.P. King "The characterization of lower molecular weight proteins by dialysis", 1958 (Box 26, Folder 15)
    In: Neuberger, A., ed. Symposium on protein structure. New York, John Wiley, pp. 104-115. Presented at 1957 July 25-29 Paris, IUPAC symposium on protein structure. Craig also attends 1957 July 18-24 Paris XVI congress of IUPAC as a member of the NAS-NRC delegation.
    Correspondence; preliminary and final programs; galley proof of ms; also 2 photocopied pages from C&EN 1957 July citing IUPAC XVI congress information.
  - A. Stracher and L.C. Craig "Characterization studies with subtilin", 1959 (Box 26, Folder 16)
    JACS 81, 696-700.
    Correspondence; 2 reviews of ms; copies of Sacks and Pence and Alderton and Snell mss on subtilin A; working material (rewrite of part of ms).
  - R.J. Hill and L.C. Craig "Counter-current distribution studies with adult human hemoglobin", 1959 (Box 26, Folder 17)
    JACS 81, 2272.
    Copy of ms and print of figure 1.
  - W. Konigsberg and L.C. Craig "Cellulose ion exchange and rotatory dispersion studies with the bacitracin polypeptides", 1959 (Box 26, Folder 18)
    JACS 81, 3452-3458.
    Figures 2,4,5 only 1960 L.C. Craig.
  - L.C. Craig. "Partition", 1960 (Box 26, Folder 19)
    In: Alexander, P., and Block, R.J., eds., Laboratory manual of analytical methods of protein chemistry (including polypeptides). New York, Pergamon Press, v.l, pp. 121-160 Correspondence, galley proof with corrections and photocopy of ms; corrected bibliography and figures. [Reprint of this ms not with collected papers].
  - L.C. Craig "Fractionation and characterization by dialysis", 1960 (Box 26, Folder 20)
    Galley proof and typescript of ms; corrected bibliography.
    In: Alexander, P., and Block, R.J., eds., Laboratory manual of analytical methods of protein chemistry (including polypeptides). New York, Pergamon Press, v. 1, pp. 103-119.
  - P. Marfey, L.C. Craig and E.N. Harvey "Isolation studies with cypridina luciferin", 1961 (Box 26, Folder 21)
    Arch biochem biophys 92, 301-311.
    Partial typescript and partial handwritten copy of ms with corrections and graphs (some used as figures).